A Finding Aid to the Alfred Victor Frankenstein Papers, 1875-1985, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Alfred Victor Frankenstein papers
1875-1985
Archives of American Art
Frankenstein, Alfred V. (Alfred Victor), 1906-1981
AAA.franalfr
Archival Resource Key
19.1 Linear feet
The papers of art critic and historian Alfred Victor Frankenstein measure 19.1 linear feet and date from 1875 to 1985. The bulk of the collection consists of Frankenstein's research and writing files on American painting, particularly artists working in the nineteenth-century. There are extensive files on artists John Haberle, William Michael Harnett, and William Sidney Mount. The collection also includes biographical material, correspondence, general writings and notes, professional activities files, personal business records, printed materials, photographs, and unidentified sound recordings.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Existence and Location of Copies
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 1373-1377, 2398-2399, and 3482 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Related Materials
Also found among the holdings of the Archives of American Art are two oral histories with Alfred Frankenstein, one conducted by Mary McChesney on November 9th, 1965 and the other conducted by Paul Karlstrom from 1978 to 1979. Additionally, Frankenstein donated one sketchbook and twelve loose sketches that are cataloged as a separate collection: the William Harnett sketches, 1870.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Alfred Frankenstein donated some of his papers in 1972, and lent materials for microfilming in 1978. His estate, handled by his son John Frankenstein, donated the materials original loaned as well as additional records in 1981.
Scope and Contents
The papers of art critic and historian Alfred Victor Frankenstein measure 19.1 linear feet and date from 1875 to 1985. The bulk of the collection consists of Frankenstein's research and writing files on American painting, particularly artists working in the nineteenth-century. There are extensive files on artists John Haberle, William Michael Harnett, and William Sidney Mount. The collection also includes biographical material, correspondence, general writings and notes, professional activities files, personal business records, printed materials, photographs, and unidentified sound recordings.
Biographical materials include awards, museum passes from the 1970s, school records, and a scrapbook documenting Frankenstein's career at the San Francisco Chronicle. Also found is his father's medical school diploma.
Largely professional in nature, Frankenstein's correspondence is with galleries, museums and institutions, colleges and universities, as well as art historians and museum colleagues including Paul Jenkins, Stanton MacDonald-Wright, and Thomas E. Ripley.
General writings are on subjects such as music, art, California, and the Ronald P. Murdock art collection. It is likely that some writings may be drafts for articles that later appeared in the San Francisco Chronicle. Also found are three notebooks, a recorded interview, recorded lectures by Frankenstein and by others.
The bulk of the collection consists of Frankenstein's extensive research files on American sill-life painting in the nineteenth-century. Research topics focus primarily on artists John Haberle (including sketches by Haberle), William Michael Harnett, William Sidney Mount, and John Frederick Peto; however, some files are found for collectors, dealers, and subjects. Files are found both for the research and writing of Frankenstein's books, After the Hunt (1953) and The World of Copley: 1738-1815 (1970). Contents of the research files vary but many contain correspondence, photographs, notes and writings, provenance research, printed materials, and photocopied and original primary documents. Additional research files are also found in Series 5, Exhibition Files.
Files concerning exhibitions curated or organized by Frankenstein include Artist Self-Portraits (1974) at the National Gallery of Art, an exhibition at the California Palace of the Legion of Honor, and the World's Fair Exposition exhibition, Our Land, Our Sky Our Water: an Exhibition of American and Canadian Art (1974). Files contain loan agreements, gallery plans, photographs, writings, correspondence, and printed materials.
Frankenstein's professional activities files include material about his job as a music critic at the San Francisco Chronicle, and records documenting his participation in the American Arts Alliance and the San Francisco Arts Commission. Also found are scattered student writings, lecture notes, and some correspondence from his teaching position at the University of California, Berkeley.
An appraisal for a Joseph Decker work, the estate records of Sylvia Frankenstein, general receipts for purchases and shipping records, and vehicle ownership records comprise Frankenstein's personal business records.
Printed materials include clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, magazines, and blank postcards. Also found are eight commercial audio recordings, including a musical piece by Charles Ives on cassette, and six phonograph records that are likely of music. A cassette entitled "Heritage of American Art" may be from an exhibition of the same title held at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City in 1975. Personal photographs include snapshots of Frankenstein with his family and portraits of him, as well as a photocopy of a family photo album. The bulk of the photographs are of artwork.
There are six unidentified sound recordings.
Biographical / Historical
Alfred Victor Frankenstein (1906-1981) was an art historian, writer, art and music critic, and educator active in San Francisco, California.
Frankenstein was born in 1906 in Chicago, Illinois. He studied at the University of Chicago but moved to San Francisco to take a job as a music critic for the San Francisco Chronicle. Later, the position expanded to include critiques of visual art and art exhibitions. He remained at the San Francisco Chronicle until 1979, concentrating only on art from 1965.
He was an expert on 19th century American still-life and his notable book, After The Hunt (1953), examined the American trompe-l'œil movement in late 19th century and early 20th-century through the work of painters William Harnett and John Frederick Peto. He also authored The World of Copley: 1738-1815 in 1970. Frankenstein curated several major exhibitions, including American Self-Portraits (1974) at the National Portrait Gallery and the 1974 World's Fair Exposition exhibition, Our Land, Our Sky Our Water: an Exhibition of American and Canadian Art..
An educator, Frankenstein was a professor of Art History at the University of California at Berkeley (1940-1974), Stanford University (1973-1981), and at Mills College (1945-1974), where he also taught American music.
Interviews; Art, American; Photographs; Sound recordings; Art -- Collectors and collecting; Art criticism -- United States; Art critics -- California -- San Francisco; Sketches; Scrapbooks; Art historians -- California -- San Francisco; National Gallery of Art (U.S.); Peto, John Frederick, 1854-1907; Haberle, John, 1856-1933; Copley, John Singleton, 1738-1815; Murdock, Roland P.; Decker, Joseph, 1853-1924; American Arts Alliance; Harnett, William Michael, 1848-1892; Ives, Charles, 1874-1954; California Palace of the Legion of Honor; San Francisco Chronicle (Firm); Mount, William Sidney, 1807-1868; Macdonald-Wright, Stanton, 1890-1973; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.); Jenkins, Paul, 1923-2012
- Biographical Material, 1875-1978; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Box 1, 21
  Scope and Contents
  Found are awards, passes for various museums and institutions, an alumni directory from the Francis W. Parker school, and a mixed media scrapbook which concerns Frankenstein's career with the San Francisco Chronicle. Also found is his father, Victor Frankenstein's diploma from medical school.
  - Awards, 1963-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Museum Passes, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - School Records, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Victor Frankenstein, Diploma, 1875; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1946-1980; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1
  Correspondence primarily concerns professional activities, research, and general inquiries. Letters are from the Downtown Gallery (Edith Halpert) and other galleries, institutions, museums, colleges and universities. Correspondents include Paul Jenkins, Stanton McDonald-Wright, Thomas E. Ripley, and numerous art historians and museum curators. A letter to Frankenstein from Stanton Macdonald-Wright dated January 8, 1972, discusses Synchromism, Orphism, and the difference between the two groups, making reference to the work of Robert Delaunay and Morgan Russell.
  - Downtown Gallery (Halpert, Edith), 1948-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, First Names Only, 1946-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 1946-1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1952-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1960-1965; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - General, 1967-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - General, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General, 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - General, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General, 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General, 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Writings and Notes, 1940-1978; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Box 1-2
  General writings include three notebooks, writings and recorded lectures by Frankenstein about music, art, or both, California, and the Ronald P. Murdock art collection. There are written entries to the Dictionary of American Biography, drafts of articles (likely for the San Francisco Chronicle), and copies of published articles. Works by others include eight lectures concerning early Northern California art recorded on three cassettes, and a cassette tape of an interview by C. Hoover.
  General writings do not include manuscripts for Frankenstein's books or exhibition catalogs. These are found in Series 4, Research Files and Series 5, Exhibition Files, reflecting the original order of the papers.
  - Notebooks, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18-20)
  - General, by Alfred Victor Frankenstein, 1940-circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-15)
  - Lectures, by Alfred Victor Frankenstein, 1970s; Archival Resource Key; 3 Cassette tapes (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Lectures, by Others, 1976; Archival Resource Key; 1 Cassette tape (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Interview, C. Hoover, 1978; Archival Resource Key; 1 Cassette tape (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - General, by Others, 1940s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19-24)
- Research and Project Files, circa 1880s-1977; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 10 Linear feet Boxes 2-12
  The bulk of the papers consist of Frankenstein's research and project files. For the most part, the files retain the original folder titles and reflect either artist's name or the names of dealers, collectors, general subjects, and a few named project files. There is extensive research material on artists Karel Appel, Christo, John F. Francis, Richard LaBarre Goodwin, John Haberle, William Michael Harnett, William Sidney Mount, and John Frederick Peto, among others. Research material concerning Frankenstein's book After the Hunt (1953) is found within the folders for William Henry Harnett. And manuscript drafts of The World of Copley: 1738-1815 (1970) are found within the research files for William Singleton Copley. There are also files containing research materials and drafts for the exhibition and published catalog, The Reality of Appearance (1970).
  There are three project files on Hawaiian painted churches, a panorama of American painting, and the tapestries of Villanueva, New Mexico.
  Content of the files vary but often contain contain correspondence between Frankenstein and collectors, dealers, or museums; photographs and slides of works of art; notebooks, notes and drafts of manuscripts, articles, and books; provenance research information; annotated printed material; and original and xeroxed primary source research material. A few files also contain sketches (notably by John Haberle).
  Users should note that there is some overlap between the Research Files in Series 4 and Exhibition Files in Series 5.
  - Multiple Artists, General, 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Multiple Artists, General, 1927-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
    Oversized material housed in Box 21, Folder 3
  - Alexander, Henry, 1949-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Appel, Karel, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13-17)
  - Atkinson, Jacob, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Baker, Harry H., 1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bement, Williams B., 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Berry-Hill Galleries Inc., 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Blanchi, A., 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Blemly, Scrapbook, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Brawn, A.D., 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Brookes, Samuel Marsden, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Brooks, Nicholas A., 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Browere, Alburtis, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Chalfont, J.D., 1940-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Chalfont, J.D., 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Christo, 1970-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Colyer, Edward, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Combes, Voltaire, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Cooper, Astley, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Copley, William Singleton, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7-13)
  - Counterfeiting, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Danton, F., 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Davies, Kenneth, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Davis, William M., 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Decker, Joseph, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Dubrevil, V., 1948-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Dunlap, William, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Elmer, Edwin Romanzo, 1953-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Fakes, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Francis, John F., 1940-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23-26)
  - Friedlander, Camila, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "Get 'Em" (Research Leads), 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Goodwin, Richard LaBarre, 1910-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
  - Gouy, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Grier, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Haberle, John, 1880s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 33-35)
  - Haberle, John, 1939-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Harnett, B.J., 1931-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4-6)
  - Harnett, William Michael, 1880s-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7-29)
  - Harnett, William Michael, 1880s-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1-23)
  - Heade, Martin Johnson, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Hirst, Claude R., 1893-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Keane, William, 1952-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - King, C.B., 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Lee Mansion, Marblehead, Massachusetts, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Lemon, Daniel, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - McLaughlin, Vincent, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Martin, Silas, 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mason, 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
  - Meissonier, J. LE, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Meurer, C.A., 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Minor Artists, 1947-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13-14)
  - Mount, William Sidney, circa 1923-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15-33)
  - Mount, William Sidney, circa 1923-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1-14)
  - Mount, William Sidney, circa 1923-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1-25)
  - Mount, William Sidney, circa 1917-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1-16)
  - Muncy, Milton A., 1962-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Peale, James and Margaretta, 1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Peale, Raphael, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Peale, Rubens, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Peto, John Frederick, 1940s-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 21-24)
  - Peto, John Frederick, 1900-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11)
    - Correspondence, Writings, and Printed Material, 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Photographs of John Frederick Peto, Studio, and Works of Art, 1900; 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Photographs of Works of Art, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Photographs of Works of Art, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Photographs of Works of Art, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Photographs and Negatives of Works of Art, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Negatives of Works of Art, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Negatives of Works of Art, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Pfleger, 1947; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Platt, George W., 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Platt, George W., circa 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Platt, George W., 1900s-1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Pollock, Jackson, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Pope, Alexander, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 14-15)
  - Radio Programs, 1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Roesen, R., 1951-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Shinn, John Marion, 1948-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Stereoscopic Photographs, 1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Stewart, Theodore, circa 1890-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 21-22)
  - Still-Life, 1940s-1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 11, Folder 23-25)
  - Stralen, Donald, circa 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Vanderlyn, John, 1943-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Vellut, 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Waas, Martin, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Walton, Richard Guy, circa 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Yates, Y. H., 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Yuel, Claude, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Multiple Artists, General Material, from Box 3, F11, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Projects, Archival Resource Key (Box 12)
    - Hawaiian Painted Churches, Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 8-12)
    - Panorama of American Painting, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 13-14)
    - Villanueva Tapestry Project, 1974-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 15-16)
- Exhibition Files, 1940s-1970s; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Boxes 12-13
  Files are found for a few exhibitions curated by Frankenstein including American Self-Portraits (1974) at the National Portrait Gallery and the 1974 World's Fair Exposition exhibition, Our Land, Our Sky Our Water: an Exhibition of American and Canadian Art. (1974). There are also files for an exhibition at the California Palace of the Legion of Honor, and an American Still Life exhibition in the 1940s.
  Files for the exhibition of artist's self-portraits also contain reserach materials on numerous artists, such as Evan Albright, Audubon, Will Barnet, Alexander Calder, John Gadsby Chapman, Chuck Close, Frank Duveneck, Philip Evergood, Robert Fulton, Ignaz Gaugengigl, Paul Georges, Arshile Gorky, Ann Hall, Morris Hirschfield, Edward Hopper, Daniel Huntington, Peter Hurd, David Claypoole Johnston, Olaf Krans, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Alfred Leslie, Helen Lundeberg, Reginald Marsh, Elizabeth Metcalf, Samuel Morse, John Sloan, Saul Steinberg, Samuel Lovett Waldo, and Tom Wesselmann.
  There is a letter from Romare Bearden in the file on the exhibition for the World's Fair Exposition of 1974.
  Files generally contain loan agreements, shipping records, photographs, slides, and transparencies of works of art, writings, correspondence between collectors, museums, and dealers and Frankenstein, and printed exhibition catalogs and announcements.
  Users should note that some of the research files found in Series 4 also contain materials concerning these exhibitions and others.
  - American Still-Life, 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Artist Self-Portraits, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 12, Folder 18-27)
  - Artist Self-Portraits, 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 1-3)
  - California Palace of the Legion of Honor Exhibition, 1940s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Expo '74, World's Fair, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 5-11)
  - Our Land, Our Sky, Our Water: an Exhibition of American and Canadian Art (1974), 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
- Professional Activities Files, 1926-1977; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 1.4 Linear feet Boxes 13-14
  Professional activities' files document Frankenstein's membership in the American Arts Alliance and the San Francisco Arts Commission. Also found here is material documenting his role as a music critc. Teaching files for his tenure at University of California, Berkeley are arranged in this series.
  - American Arts Alliance, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Conference Material, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Museum of Modern Art, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Music Critic Material, circa 1940s-1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 13, Folder 17-21)
  - Music Critic Material, 1926-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 1-3)
  - San Francisco Arts Commission, 1970-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 4-11)
  - Teaching Files, 1958-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 14, Folder 12-21)
- Personal Business Records, 1956-1977; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders Box 14
  Found is an appraisal for a work by Joseph Decker, although it is unclear whether Frankenstein owned the painting; estate records of Sylvia Frankenstein; scattered receipts for everyday purchases and shipping records; and records regarding the purchase and registration of a vehicle.